Hello, welcome back to our course. Today, we are going to talk about graphics in R.
Alright, so the very first function to use, once we would like to plot something, is the function plot()
and then we need to pass it two vectors of the same length.
For example, here you can see that I passed to it a vector x
and then a vector y and, as a result, you can see that I have this plot with x on the x-axis
and y on the y-axis. And here you can see that I also inserted that line par() where I set bg = "grey"
and this is for a better visibility because of the captions.
We could also pass a simple two-column data frame or a matrix to plot().
So here you can see that I loaded the pressure dataset and then I would like to see how the pressure dataset looks like. So a first few lines are temperature
and pressure and you can see that there are numeric values.
And now, once I pass it to plot function plot(), you can see that, indeed, on the
x-axis, I have temperature, on the y-axis, I have pressure and then my curve is actually here, plotted using this
points. There are many different ways in which I could save my plot, but there is a handy way in R using these graphics devices.
So here, I could save a plot to a PDF, PNG, or another format
and then after, basically, asking R to save it, I need to close the device. So here you can see an example, so if I ask to save it to PDF, I need to select the name of the file and then the width and the height of the plot, then I
select what I would like to save and then I need to close that device.
There are many different ways we could customize our R plots and then here we could basically pass many parameters.
For example, we could adjust labels, so here, axes labels, xlab and ylab. We could adjust the size of the labels, using this cex.lab .
We could also adjust the range of the axes
using xlim, ylim and there are many different parameters. You can have a look at the help function using this ?par .
But there are also other customization we could do. For example, we could change the point symbol, colors
size, etc. For example, to change a point symbol, we use this parameter pch()
and then we have many symbols, from 0 to 25, then we could change a color, using color(), and then we could also change the size, using this cex
parameter. We could also add to our plot, to our graphics,
the title and of course we could change the titles of our axes. So, for example, to add the title to our plot we use this parameter main
and to adjust the titles of the axes we use xlab and ylab.
Alternative way to add a title of a plot is just to use the separate function title().
And, here there are many different types our curve on a plot can look like:
"p" stands for points (you have already seen it in the very first plot), "l" for
this solid lines,"b" for both, "h" for histogram (basically vertical bars) etc, etc.
Okay, let us look at the examples: So here, once again
I'm plotting this pressure data and now I'm selecting type = "p", so this stands for
points, once again, and then as my title, I'm selecting main = "pressure data"
and you can see that now I have my plot with a title.
If I'd like to change the type of the curve
from points to a solid line, then I could select a select type = "l" and then you can see that now I can see that solid line.
We could also select type = "b", which means both points and the lines and then here you can see that I also added
the title to the plot and I passed the title through that parameter main = "pressure data".
Here you can see that, instead of a line, I have this vertical bars
and (if this is something you would fancy) then definitely could choose it.
And we could also add another symbols and lines to our plot. For example, we could add grid and a legend.
So if you would like to add vertical and horizontal lines
we could use this abline(h = seq(.,.,.)) and select the particular vector
for telling where the line should be. And then we could also use this abline(v = seq(.,.,.)) to add vertical lines. And once again,
I could pass them through that parameter v and then I could basically tell R at which
points that vertical line should be added. So here, once again, let us look at the example: So, we have
once again our plot. I passed pressure data, and now the type = "p", so I have points
and then here you can see that I would like to add this horizontal lines.
So, I passed to parameter h the sequence from 50 to 200 and then the step size is 50. So we can see that I added horizontal lines
from 50 to 200, and then the step size is 50, yeah? So we have this horizontal lines added. Now, I would like to also add vertical lines.
I would like to add vertical lines from 100 to 600 by 100, so you can see that I added the first line, then the second line
and the third line. And then there is also another way, we could also use this parameter grid( ), where,
basically, it shows me the grid in my plotting window. So here I added the grid, here you can see this is in this,
blue color, light blue color, so basically nx and ny
are to select the number of cells and then here you can see that we will have
two cells on the this x-dimension, 1 and 2, and then four cells
for the y-axis: 1, 2, 3, 4.
And we can also add a legend, so then we are going to see how to add the legend.
We could also add text to our plotting window. So here, once again, I'm calling my data pressure
and then I would like to add a line
but instead of selecting type = "l": How can I do it? I just plot pressure without any parameters
and then I add this another function, lines(pressure). So you can see that lines(),
basically, it's for plotting lines in our plotting windows, so here, the default was a plot with
points and now, by selecting this lines(pressure), I added on top of that
a line. And then here, I could also add a text, as I said. How can I do it? Well, I select the position of the text. So, the position of the text, the first
I select X axis, so here, on the x-axis I have 150, okay? And then, on the y-axis, here, we selected 200, so that
corresponds to that particular place. And what is the label? The label here would be "Hello".
We could also add mathematical expressions to our plot. We could include symbols in the text and the labels of the plots
and symbols are available as expressions and there is this handy function called
bquote(), we could use here. Alright, so now let us define this new vector X and I'm defining it using the sequence function, so I would like to have values from minus 2 to 2 and then the length is 200.
And then here, I would like to plot on the x-axis x
and then on the y-axis, I would like to plot density
of these points and then I'm assuming that these points
coming from a normal distribution, so I would like to plot the density of a normal distribution and then the type = "l",
so line. Now, how can I add a text? So here, we define these two parameters, mu is zero, variance is 1.
And then, I could add text using this text function, so basically first, once again, I need to select the position where
the text appears, so I would need to find 0 on the x-axis, 0.2 on the y-axis
and the position tells me the position of the label relative to x and y. So, pos = 1 puts the label just below the point 0, 0.2.
And then, how can I add the label? So, we use that function bquote() to label.
Then, I use paste() and then what label I would like to add. I would like to write that there is a "normal density", then I would like to paste it with mu. Mu will be
a mathematical symbol, mu, and then here we can see that that notation
with a dot and a mu in parentheses ".(mu)" refers to my mu defined here. So, you'll see in the plot 0
similarly, for sigma squared, here we would have this sigma squared in the plot as a symbol and then the variance here, you can see
that would refer to that second parameter. Okay, so how does it look like?
It looks like this, so indeed, we had these values from minus 2 to 2 on the x-axis,
the density on the y-axis, then we indeed have a normal density and then
we selected the place where the text should appear and then our text is "normal density mu=0", and "sigma^2=1".
Okay, let me stop here and then we are going to come back to graphics in the next video. Thank you!